Contact

+919972033224 (Mobile) praveenkshanmugam@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/praveen-kumar-40537a17 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Java

Spring Boot

SpringMVC

Languages

English

Tamil

praveen kumar

Senior Software Engineer at Lowe's Companies, Inc.

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Summary

Around 7.5 years of experience in Product Development using Core Java, Spring Boot, Micro Services, JPA, Web Services, Design Patterns, Data Structures and Algorithms.

Strong working experience in Java 8 (functional programming), Spring framework, Spring Web Flux Reactive framework, Microservice's Ecosystem Design and implementation using Spring Boot 2, Rest Web Services, Apache Kafka (Messaging and queuing system).

Working Experience in Containerized Environment using Docker and Kubernetes in Google Cloud Platform(GCP).

CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins and Spinnaker.

Good Knowledge and work experience on designing OLAP and OLTP systems and expertise in ETL Development with Database design knowledge.

Experience

Lowe's Companies, Inc. Senior Software Engineer August 2018 - Present (2 years)

Bengaluru Area, India

Accenture

Senior Java Developer August 2015 - July 2018 (3 years)

Bengaluru Area, India

Roles and Responsibilities:

Worked on Security Management Product as part of Accenture Inovation Inc-Digital Team which procured \$200 million in revenue on first release.

Page 1 of 3

Designed and developed various important features for traders and sales people.

Designed complete middle tier service layer using frameworks like spring boot, Microservices. Proposed and presented a performance improvement project to Executive Directors and successfully implemented the distributed caching system using Hazelcast with Kryo serializer.

Involved in designing of the OLAP database design and also played a major role in database development including ETL process.

Cornerstone OnDemand
Java Developer
January 2014 - July 2015 (1 year 7 months)
Bangalore

Coordinating with Architects and involved in the development of major middle tier services.

Implemented the ETL process by pulling the data from various clients and perform predictive calculus using MapReduce and pushes the computed data into

Hadoop HBase ecosystem.

Developed Evolv Insights from the scratch which involves the attrition analysis for various clients.

##Written test cases for service layers in the application with Mockito and JUnit test steps.

Dell

Developer (Bl developer & DBA) January 2011 - December 2013 (3 years) Bangalore

Roles and Responsibilities:

- # Taken initiative and completed the module under the guidance of Tech Lead
- # Involved in designing phases of workflow lifecycle management
- # Involved in designing the data model and ER diagrams for the entire lifecycle
- # Developing and configuring the Database Infrastructure for the Application, including the Data warehouse systems
- # Performed the query optimization on the critical module and improved the performance by 35% and got appreciated by higher level managers

Education

Anna University

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.), Computers · (2006 - 2010)

Activity

06/28/2020, praveen kumar added candidate to Senior Software Engineer